<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sinners sanctuary. By Thomas Packer, his Majesties servant</title>
            <author>Packer, Thomas, fl. 1628-1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08799</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19084</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103145</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838902</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838902</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3292</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08799)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3292)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1212:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sinners sanctuary. By Thomas Packer, his Majesties servant</title>
                  <author>Packer, Thomas, fl. 1628-1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 108 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Haviland, for Edward Blackmore, and are to be sold at his shop in S. Pauls churchyard at the signe of the Angel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Some print faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Forgiveness of sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3292:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3292:1"/>
            <p>THE SINNERS Sanctuary.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISA. 7.55.</hi>
               </bibl> Let the wicked forſake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts; and let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne unto the Lord, and hee will have mercy upon him; and to our God, for hee will abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly pardon.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HIERON.</hi>
               </bibl> The Lord doth neither performe the good things which he promiſed to the Saints, if they returne to iniquities; nor the evils which hee threatned to ſinners, if they returne unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</q>
            <p>By THOMAS PACKER, his Majeſties Servant.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Haviland,</hi> for <hi>Edward Blackmore,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church yard at the ſigne of the Angel, 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3292:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3292:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CHILDREN of Men.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 3.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>For all have ſinned and come ſhort of the glory of God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ome now,<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.18.</note> and let us reaſon to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſaith the Lord; though your ſins be as ſcarlet, they ſhall be as white as ſnow; though they be red like crymſin, they ſhall be as wooll.</p>
            <p>Have I any pleaſure at<note place="margin">Ezec. 18.23</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:3292:3"/>
all, that the wicked ſhould die, ſaith the Lord God? and not that hee ſhould returne from his waies, and live?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">31.</note>Caſt away from you all your tranſgreſſions, whereby yee have tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, and make you a new heart, and a new ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: for why will ye die, O houſe of Iſrael?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Sa. 12.23.</note>I will teach you the good and the right way.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">24.</note>Onely feare the Lord, and ſerve him in truth, with all your heart: for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider how great things he hath done for you.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3292:3"/>Wee muſt ſerve the Lord, our God,<note place="margin">Deu. 28.47</note> with joi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and with glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of all things.</p>
            <p>Truſt in the Lord with all thine heart,<note place="margin">Pro. 35.</note> and leane not unto thine owne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</p>
            <p>In all thy waies ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him,<note place="margin">6.</note> and hee ſhall direct thy paths.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed is that man that maketh the Lord his truſt.<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And be not conformed to this world;<note place="margin">Rom. 12.2</note> but be yee transformed by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of your mind, that ye may prove what
<pb facs="tcp:3292:4"/>
is that good, that accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and perfect will of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtin.</note>Doe not underſtand that thou maiſt beleeve, but beleeve that thou maiſt underſtand; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is the reward of Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 11.40</note>Jeſus ſaith unto <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> Said I not unto thee, that if thou wouldeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, thou ſhouldeſt ſee the glory of God?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Act. 18.27.</note>When <hi>Apollos</hi> came into Achaia, hee helped them much, who had beleeved through grace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 7.9.</note>If ye will not beleeve,
<pb facs="tcp:3292:4"/>
ſurely yee ſhall not bee eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>We beeleve, and know,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.69.</note> that thou art Chriſt, that Sonne of the living God.</p>
            <p>Teach me good judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and knowledge,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.66.</note> O Lord; for I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved thy Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>It belongeth to every private man to judge of the doctrine of religion,<note place="margin">Brentius.</note> [for ſatisfaction of his owne conſcience] and to diſcerne the truth from falſhood.</p>
            <p>That Religion which<note place="margin">Lipſius.</note> is ſincerely taken out of
<pb facs="tcp:3292:5"/>
the holy Scriptures, is the true, and Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Andrad.</note>For they containe the moſt ample Canon, that is, the rule, and ſquare of Piety, Faith, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note>They have delivered unto us, that there is but one God, and one Chriſt; one Hope, and one Faith; one Church, and one Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ferus.</note>They are the ſole rule of veritie; and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver differs, or contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth the ſame, it is error, and cockle, with what
<pb facs="tcp:3292:5"/>
ſhew ſoever it commeth forth.</p>
            <p>They are all plaine to him that underſtandeth,<note place="margin">Pro. 3.5.</note> and right to them that finde knowledge.</p>
            <p>All thoſe things which appertaine to faith,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> and direction of life, are laid downe plainly in the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>They are manifeſt to them,<note place="margin">Epiphan.</note> who repaire unto them, with a religious heart.</p>
            <p>Let not our Religion therefore conſiſt in our fantaſies; for any truth,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> whatſoever it be, is better
<pb facs="tcp:3292:6"/>
than any thing, that can of our own head be deviſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note>Godly humility doth more eaſily finde out the Maker of the ſtars, than proud curioſity the order of the ſtarres.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Booke of nature into the book of Grace.</note>The depth of Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and the manner of Regeneration are diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult points of divine my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, which a ſtudious Divine, an illuminated ſpirit cannot find out.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>Let us religiouſly adore theſe things by faith, and not curiouſly ſearch into them by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, further than Gods
<pb facs="tcp:3292:6"/>
Word doth allow.</p>
            <p>This is the perfection of the regenerate;<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> If they acknowledge themſelves to be imperfect.</p>
            <p>The doctrine of the holy Ghoſt doth not encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage curioſitie,<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> but infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth charitie.</p>
            <p>When the ſoule is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome by the fever,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> or fiery heat of imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then it queſtioneth; but when it is ſound, and in good temper, it reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not, but faithfully beleeveth.</p>
            <p>As zeale muſt erect our diſcretion,<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> that wee run
<pb facs="tcp:3292:7"/>
not too ſlowly; So diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion muſt direct our zeale, that we run not too faſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note>God will reveale wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome onely to ſuch as walke continually in the way of peace; not in the way of preciſeneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Harſnet.</note>Tell me, what is not contained in the ten Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, which of a Chriſtian is to bee performed?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Lactant.</note>When God opened his truth unto us, he would have us know thoſe things only which it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooved man to know for
<pb facs="tcp:3292:7"/>
obtaining life: But of thoſe things, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertained to curious, &amp; profane deſires, he ſpake not, that they might bee hidden. Why then doeſt thou ſeeke thoſe things which thou canſt not know? neither art thou more bleſſed, if thou knoweſt them?</p>
            <p>Grace teacheth a man to put his knowledge in practice.<note place="margin">Harſnet.</note>
            </p>
            <p>He deſires to be taught,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> that he may walke; not that he may talke, as too many doe.</p>
            <p>Adde to your faith ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.5.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:3292:8"/>
and to vertue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6.</note>And to knowledge temperance; and to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance patience; and to patience godlineſſe:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7.</note>And to godlineſſe brotherly kindneſſe; and to brotherly kindneſſe charitie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">8.</note>For if theſe things be in you, and abound, they make you, that you ſhall neither be barren, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luther in</hi> Luke 6.</note>Let us firſt repoſe Faith in God alone; and
<pb facs="tcp:3292:8"/>
then let us direct our works to the benefit of our neighbour.</p>
            <p>As many as will not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem in</hi> Epheſ. 5.</note> and walke in love, and I ſhew forth their faith by their works, are neither the ſons of God, nor heires of his kingdom.</p>
            <p>What doth it profit,<note place="margin">Ia. 2.14.</note> my brethren, though a man ſay hee hath faith? can faith ſave him?</p>
            <p>The end of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is Charity,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.5.</note> out of a pure heart, and of a good conſcience, and of faith unfeined.</p>
            <p>By faith which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived<note place="margin">Haymo.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:3292:9"/>
in the heart, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed with the mouth, and adorned with good works, the juſt man li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth eternally.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cyprian.</note>Life is here loſt, or wonne; everlaſting ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is here provided for, by the due worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of God, and the fruits of faith.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Epiphan.</note>For in the age to come, after a mans death, there is no more helpe by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, no more calling to penance, no more exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of Almes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Epiphan.</note>It is as the corne, that ſwelleth not, after it is
<pb facs="tcp:3292:9"/>
reaped, neither can bee ſpoiled with the wind.</p>
            <p>The garners are ſealed up, the time is paſt,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> the combat is finiſhed, the liſts are voided, and the garlands are given.<note place="margin">Aug.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Let us therefore bee at one with the word of God, while we are in this life, for when we are gone out of this world, there ſhall bee no more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction, or ſatisfaction; there remaineth no more, but the Judge, the Gao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and the Priſon.</p>
            <p>When wee were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.10.</note> we were reconciled
<pb facs="tcp:3292:10"/>
unto God, by the death of his Son.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9.26.</note>Once in the end of the world hath he appeared to put away ſin, by the ſacrifice of himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Acts 10.43.</note>To him give all the Prophets witneſſe, that, through his name, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever beleeveth in him, ſhall receive remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Bellar.</note>Wee confeſſe, that Chriſt hath truly, yea moſt fully ſatisfied God the Father for us, and for the whole world.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note>JESUS CHRIST taking upon him the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
<pb facs="tcp:3292:10"/>
but not the fault, hath therby blotted out both the fault, and the puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Let us hold faſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our faith,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wavering, for hee is faithfull that promiſed.</p>
            <p>The rule of Catholike faith is certain &amp; known.<note place="margin">Bellar.</note>
            </p>
            <p>There is nothing more knowne,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> nothing more certain, than the holy Scriptures, which are contained in the writings of the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</p>
            <p>They are Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> which be of ſound
<pb facs="tcp:3292:11"/>
Faith, and good life.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Idem.</note>Hereticks doe violate faith by beleeving falſe things of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Tertul.</note>Whatſoever favoureth againſt the truth, is an hereſie, be it never ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienta cuſtome.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note>And ſchiſmatiks (though they beleeve the ſame things with us, yet) doe fly from brotherly Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, by their wicked di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Idem.</note>Wherefore neither doth the Heretick belong to the Catholike Church, becauſe hee loveth not God:</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3292:11"/>Nor the Schiſmatike,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> becauſe he loveth not his neighbour.</p>
            <p>Pure Religion,<note place="margin">Ja. 1.27.</note> and undefiled before GOD, and the Father, is this, To viſit the fatherleſſe, and the widowes in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction; and to keepe himſelfe unſpotted from the world.</p>
            <p>If true charity,<note place="margin">Caſarius.</note> and humility be wanting, we ought not to preſume, and truſt to the habit on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Religion.</p>
            <p>Let us ſearch,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.40.</note> and try our waies, and turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine unto the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3292:12"/>
               <note place="margin">25.</note>The Lord is good to them that wait for him; to the ſoule that ſeeketh him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">30.</note>For hee doth not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict willingly; nor grieve the Children of Men.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 PET. 2.17.</bibl>
               <q>Feare God. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor the King.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:3292:12"/>
            <head>The contents are theſe, viz.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe Sinners converſion. <hi>Pa. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His godly deſire. <hi>4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His comming unto God. <hi>7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Repentance. <hi>10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Confeſſion. <hi>15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Abſolution. <hi>19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His amendment of life. <hi>23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His aſſurance of Salvation. <hi>30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gods mercy. <hi>34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Death. <hi>40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The laſt Iudgement. <hi>44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Helps to the amendment of life. <hi>1.</hi> Prayer. <hi>51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Reading the Scriptures. <hi>55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Hearing the Word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. <hi>59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Sacraments. <hi>62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The holy Euchariſt, or Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Body and Bloud of our Lord. <hi>64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A remembrance of the death, and paſſion of our Saviour Chriſt. <hi>68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Worthy Receivers. <hi>70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3292:13"/>Vnworthy Receivers. <hi>74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tranſubſtantiation. <hi>76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To be received in both kinds. <hi>80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Prayer before receiving the Communion. <hi>83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Prayer after receiving the Communion. <hi>85</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer before reading the holy Scriptures. <hi>87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for faith. <hi>88</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For Repentance. <hi>89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A ſhort and effectuall Prayer. <hi>90</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The generall Confeſsion. <hi>91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for the Morning. <hi>93</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for all times. <hi>95</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer before going to bed <hi>96</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Pſalme of contrition, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion. <hi>98</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Pſalme for remiſsion. <hi>100</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Pſalme for mercy, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>102</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Pſalme of confidence in Gods mercie. <hi>104</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Pſalme of praiſe. <hi>106</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3292:13"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE SINNERS Converſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Iſrael,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.1.</note> returne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord thy God; for thou haſt fallen by thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</p>
               <p>Returne unto mee,<note place="margin">Malac. 3.7</note> and I will returne unto you, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</p>
               <p>Our converſion will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies finde him prepared.<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Humble your ſelves there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore under the mighty hand of God,<note place="margin">Iam. 4.10.</note> that hee may exalt you in due time.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3292:14"/>
                  <note place="margin">Lyra in Eph.</note>Humility is the foundation of the ſpirituall building.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 4.8.</note>Draw nigh to God, and he will draw nigh to you.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. Naz.</note>O the readineſſe of Gods gratious love! O the eaſineſſe of his exorable reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment!</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Perkins.</note>A man beginning to bee converted, is at that inſtant the childe of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Idem.</note>Inward motions, and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Gods Spirit, are the materiall beginning of a Sinners converſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3.13.</note>For it is God that worketh in you, both to will, and to doe, of his good pleaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 15.</note>The prodigall ſon, when he came to himſelfe, ſaid: I will ariſe, and goe to my father, and will ſay unto him; Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I have ſinned againſt Heaven, and before thee;</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3292:14"/>And am no more worthy to be called thy ſonne,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> make me as one of thy hired ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
               <p>And he aroſe,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> and came to his father. But when he was yet a great way off, his father ſaw him, and had compaſſion, and ran, and fell on his neck, and kiſſed him.</p>
               <p>Though a man come to the height of vice,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> and yet be willing to returne into the way of vertue, God recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, and embraceth him wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly.</p>
               <p>None ought therefore to deſpaire of pardon,<note place="margin">Greg.</note> if about the end of their life they turne to repentance.</p>
               <p>And although our conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion be good in our laſt ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; yet is that better,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> which is performed long before our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3292:15"/>
death; that wee may with more ſecurity paſſe out of this world.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron.</note>God grant the ſinner may be as ſoone turned to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as the Lord is ready to change his determined judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ezech. 33.</note>Turne yee, turne ye from your evill waies; for why will ye dye, O houſe of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lam. 15.</note>Turne thou us unto thee, O Lord, and wee ſhall bee turned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His godly deſire.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.</note>AS the Hart panteth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the water brookes, ſo panteth my ſoule after thee, O God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">84.</note>My ſoule longeth; yea,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3292:15"/>
even fainteth for the Courts of the Lord: My heart, and my fleſh crieth out for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God.</p>
               <p>The more earneſtly God is deſired of us,<note place="margin">Gregor.</note> the more ſweetly is hee delighted in us.</p>
               <p>Our deſires doe ſound more powerfully in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creteſt eares of God,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> than our words.</p>
               <p>Hee that ſearcheth the heart,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> knoweth what is the mind of the ſpirit; becauſe he maketh interceſſion for the Saints, according to the will of God.</p>
               <p>God hath annexed a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of bleſſedneſſe,<note place="margin">Perkins.</note> and life everlaſting to the deſire of grace.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed are they which doe hunger,<note place="margin">Mat 5.</note> and thirſt after
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3292:16"/>
righteouſneſſe; for they ſhall be filled.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note>The whole life of a good Chriſtian is an holy will and deſire.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bradford.</note>God hath given thee a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, and beleeving heart, that is, an heart which deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to repent, and beleeve; for ſuch an one is taken of him for a penitent and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heart, he accepting the will for the deed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.</note>For if there bee firſt a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling mind, it is accepted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that a man hath, and not according to that a man hath not.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mnit.</note>When I have a good deſire (though it doth ſcarcely ſhew it ſelf in ſome little, &amp; ſlender ſigh) I muſt be aſſured that the Spirit of God is preſent, and worketh his good worke.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3292:16"/>He will fulfill the deſire of them that feare him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.</note> he will alſo heare their cry, and ſave them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His comming unto God.</head>
               <p>HEe that commeth unto God,<note place="margin">Hebr. 11.</note> muſt beleeve that he is, and that he is a rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of them that diligently ſeeke him.</p>
               <p>Let us draw neere with a true heart,<note place="margin">10.</note> in full aſſurance of faith.</p>
               <p>In Chriſt we have boldnes,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.</note> and acceſſe, with confidence by the faith of him.</p>
               <p>The firſt comming to God,<note place="margin">Hom. de fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> is through faith, whereby we be juſtified before him.</p>
               <p>For the faith of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Religion,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> is the light of the ſoule; the doore of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3292:17"/>
life; the foundation of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſalvation.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aug.</note>Without it, no man can come neere the number of the ſons of God; without it, all the endevour of man is void.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note>For ye are all the children of God by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Beda.</note>It commeth not from the wiſdome of eloquent words; but from the gift of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly calling.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note>For unto you it is given, in the behalfe of CHRIST, not onely to beleeve on him; but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>When the Scribe ſaid, that to love GOD with all the heart, and with all the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and with all the ſoule, and with all the ſtrength; And to love his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3292:17"/>
neighbour as himſelfe, is more than all whole burnt offerings and ſacrifices:</p>
               <p>Jeſus ſaid unto him,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> thou art not farre from the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven.</p>
               <p>If thy heart can onely ſobbe unto GOD, deſpaire not,<note place="margin">Knox.</note> thou art not deſtitute of Faith; for that onely ſobbe is an acceptable Sacrifice unto GOD.</p>
               <p>The Faith which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture commendss is nothing elſe, but,<note place="margin">Ferus.</note> To truſt in the free mercy of GOD.</p>
               <p>Come unto mee all yee that labour,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.</note> and are heavie laden; and I will give you reſt.</p>
               <p>Incline your eare,<note place="margin">Iſa. 55.</note> and come unto mee; heare, and your ſoule ſhall live: and I will make an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3292:18"/>
covenant with you, even the ſure mercies of <hi>David.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His Repentance.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.</note>THe Lord is long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to us ward, not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that any ſhould periſh; but that all ſhould come to repentance.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 3.</note>Repent ye therfore, and be converted, that your ſinnes may be blotted out.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gloſ. ord.</note>Repentance is a bewayling of our former ſins, and a care not to commit the like a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note>God never deſpiſeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, if it bee offered unto him intirely and ſimply.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron.</note>For the Lord reſpecteth not the length of time; but conſidereth the upright affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3292:18"/>
of him that repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</p>
               <p>When we feele the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of our ſins,<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dall.</note> and be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in heart for them, it is the worke of the holy Ghoſt, and in time will bring forth fruit worthy of repentance.</p>
               <p>There are foure parts of true repentance.<note place="margin">Hom. de poenit.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Contrition, which is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſorrow conceived in the heart for our ſinnes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
               <p>Confeſſion, which is an <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> humble and unfained ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging of our ſins unto God.</p>
               <p>Faith whereby we ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> beleeve, that God, for his Sonne Chriſt Jeſus ſake, will forgive us all our iniquities.</p>
               <p>Amendment of life, which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> is, to become new creatures,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3292:19"/>
and to bring forth fruits wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of repentance.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aug.</note>Neither is it ſufficient to repentance, to change our manners into better, and to depart from our evill waies; unleſſe GOD be ſatisfied for our ſins paſt, by the ſorrow of repentance, by the groane of humility, by the ſacrifice of a contrite heart, Almes deeds accompanying.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note>Not to bee grieved for thy ſins, doth more diſpleaſe God, and provoke his anger, than the ſinne which before thou diddeſt commit.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ioel 2.</note>Therfore now alſo ſaith the Lord; Turne ye even to me, with all your heart, and with faſting, and with weeping, and with mourning.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>And rent your heart, and not your garments, and turne
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3292:19"/>
unto the LORD your GOD; for he is gratious, and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſlow to anger, and of great kindneſſe.</p>
               <p>When thou ſo repenteſt,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> that thy ſoule hath a bitter taſte of that, which before was pleaſant in thy life; and what before was delightfull to the body, the ſame tormenteth thee in thine heart, even now doſt thou lament, and mourne before GOD.</p>
               <p>If a man be never ſo great a ſinner,<note place="margin">Latimer.</note> yet if he have true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, with faith, and hope in GODS mercy, he ſhall be forgiven.</p>
               <p>GODS mercy hath no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits at all;<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> if any doe call for helpe, there is one that will heare readily; If any doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, there is one that will ſhew mercy.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:3292:20"/>
                  <note place="margin">Lyra moral.</note>As the Palme tree, which is rugged in the ſtocke; and hath pleaſant fruit in the top; even ſo a righteous man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth in the roughneſſe of repentance, and endeth in the ſweetneſſe of heavenly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hom de poenit.</note>Let us therefore repent for ſtraying from ſo good a Lord; let us confeſſe our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe before him; but yet let us truſt in Gods free mercy, for Chriſt Jeſus ſake, for the pardon of our ſins.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gregor.</note>For Gods mercy doth helpe thoſe who repent in this world; but in that which is to come, we doe not repent, but give account of our works.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note>Deſpiſeſt thou the riches of his goodneſſe, and forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and long ſuffering, not knowing that the goodneſſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3292:20"/>
of God leadeth thee to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His Confeſſion.</head>
               <p>HE that covereth his ſins,<note place="margin">Prov. 28.</note> ſhall not proſper, but who ſo confeſſeth, and forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them ſhall have mercie.</p>
               <p>Confeſſe thy ſinnes before God,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> and declare thine offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with prayer to the true Judge; not with thy tongue, but with remembrance of thy conſcience.</p>
               <p>That confeſſion delivereth from death,<note place="margin">Ambr.</note> which is made by repentance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David</hi> ſaid unto the Lord,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.</note> I have ſinned greatly in that I have done: And now I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, O Lord, take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the iniquity of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3292:21"/>
for I have done foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Baſil.</note>I doe not confeſſe with my lips, that I may manifeſt my ſelfe to many; but inwardly in my very heart, ſhutting mine eyes, to thee alone, that ſeeſt the things that are in ſecret, do I ſhew my groanes, roaring within my ſelfe: for the groanes of mine heart, and the lamentations ſent to thee, my God, from the depth of my ſoule, ſuffice for a confeſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hom. de poenit.</note>This is the chiefeſt, and moſt principall Confeſſion, that in the Scriptures, and Word of God, wee are bidden to make; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which, we ſhall never obtaine pardon, and forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our ſins.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bernard.</note>Without this Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3292:21"/>
the righteous man is judged unthankfull, and the ſinner reputed a dead man Ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re Conf ſſion is the way of the ſinner, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe becommeth the righteous.</p>
               <p>Lord be mercifull unto me,<note place="margin">Pſal. 41.</note> heale my ſoule, for I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt thee.</p>
               <p>If any ſay, I have ſinned,<note place="margin">Iob 33.</note> and perverted that which was right, and it profited mee not;</p>
               <p>He will deliver his ſoule from going into the pit,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> and his life ſhall ſee the light.</p>
               <p>If we will with a ſorrowfull,<note place="margin">Hom. de poenit.</note> and contrite heart, make an unfeined confeſſion of our ſins unto God, he will freely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them, and put all our wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe out of his remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:3292:22"/>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>I doe not ſay, but that if any do finde themſelves troubled in conſcience, they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire to their learned Curat, or Paſtor, or to ſome other godly learned man, and ſhew the trouble, &amp; doubt of their conſcience to him, that they may receive at his hand the comfortable ſalve of Gods word.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hom. de poenit.</note>But it is againſt the true Chriſtian liberty, that any man ſhould be bound to the numbering of his ſinnes, as hath beene uſed heretofore, in the time of blindneſſe, and ignorance.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bellar.</note>
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> admitteth of private confeſſion unto the Paſtor, when any is afflicted in his conſcience, and ſhall need an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others helpe: Yet with this moderation, that this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3292:22"/>
bee free, and not exa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cted; and not injoyning a rehearſall of all particular ſins.</p>
               <p>Let us with a true and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite heart,<note place="margin">Hom de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oenit.</note> uſe that kind of confeſſion, which God hath commanded in his word.</p>
               <p>If we confeſſe our ſins,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.</note> he is faithfull, and juſt, to forgive us our ſins; and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His Abſolution.</head>
               <p>WHo can forgive ſins,<note place="margin">Mark. 2.7.</note> but God onely?</p>
               <p>The Son of Man hath power upon earth to forgive ſins.<note place="margin">10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>He will purge your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from dead workes,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.14.</note> to ſerve the living God.</p>
               <p>For this is not an humane<note place="margin">Ambroſ.</note>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:3292:23"/>
worke, neither is the holy Ghoſt given by man; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng called upon by the Prieſt, is beſtowed by God; wherin the gift is Gods, the miniſtery is the Prieſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pet. Lumb.</note>God onely doth remit, and reteine ſins; and yet he hath given unto the Church pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of binding, and looſing. But God bindeth, and looſeth otherwiſe than the Church doth: for he by himſelfe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remitteth ſins, becauſe hee purgeth the ſoule inwardly from the ſpot of ſin, &amp; freeth it from the depth of eternall death; which the Church can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do, but hath power of bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and looſing, that is, of declaring what ſinners are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looſed, or bound.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chemnit.</note>In abſolution God himſelf, by the miniſtery of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3292:23"/>
doth remit ſins unto all beleevers.</p>
               <p>The vertue and effect of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion is not in the Diſciples,<note place="margin">Cajetan.</note> but in God, who pardoneth.</p>
               <p>We account of them,<note place="margin">Ambroſ.</note> as the Miniſters of Chriſt, &amp; Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards of the Myſteries.</p>
               <p>Sins are not looſed or retei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at the pleaſure of men;<note place="margin">Aug.</note> but according to the will of God, &amp; praiers of the Church.</p>
               <p>To the Lord our God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long mercies,<note place="margin">Daniel 9.9</note> and forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, though we have rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt him.</p>
               <p>Delivering fom ſin,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafteth righteouſnes; yea he extinguiſheth ſin, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it not to be.</p>
               <p>O Lord God Almighty,<note place="margin">Ordo Rom. antiq. de Offic divin. pag. <hi>18.</hi> edi. Rom. <hi>1591.</hi>
                  </note> be mercifull to me a ſinner, that I may worthily give thankes unto thee, who haſt made
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3292:24"/>
me an unworthy one, for thy mercies ſake, a Miniſter of the Prieſtly Office; and haſt appointed mee a poore, and humble Mediatour, to pray, and make interceſſion unto our Lord Jeſus Chriſt for ſinners, that returne unto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: And therefore, O Lord, the Ruler, who wouldeſt have all men to bee ſaved, and to come to the knowledge of the truth; who doſt not deſire the death of a ſinner, but that he may bee reconciled, and live; Receive my prayer, which I powre forth before the face of thy mercy, for thy ſervants, and handmaids, who have fled to repentance, and thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Nehemiah 9.17.</note>Thou art a God, ready to pardon, gracious, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3292:24"/>
ſlow to anger, and of great kindneſſe.</p>
               <p>Behold,<note place="margin">Ambroſ.</note> that by the holy Ghoſt ſins are forgiven; but men, to the remiſſion of ſins, bring their Miniſtery: They exerciſe not the authority of any power.</p>
               <p>Therefore in all the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, there is no dominion,<note place="margin">Optat.</note> but a Miniſtery.</p>
               <p>Almighty God give unto thee abſolution,<note place="margin">Tho. Aquin.</note> and remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His amendment of life.</head>
               <p>YOu were ſometimes darkneſſe:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.</note> but now are yee light in the Lord; walke as children of light.</p>
               <p>Set your affection on<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.</note>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:3292:25"/>
things above; not on things on the earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note>Put ye off concerning the former converſation, the old man, which is corrupt after the deceitfull luſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>And put yee on the new man, which after GOD, is created in righteouſneſſe, and true holineſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Playfer.</note>That which is borne of the old man, which is the fleſh, muſt dayly decreaſe in us, and grow downwards.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Idem.</note>But that which is borne of the new man, which is the Spirit, muſt daily increaſe in us, and grow upward.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Latymer.</note>Repentance and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, are a ſure reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that our ſins ſhall not bee our ſhame and confuſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dall.</note>Bee carefull to live in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, reforming your affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3292:25"/>
inwardly; and your converſation outwardly, ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cording to the preſcript rule of God word.</p>
               <p>They that from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of their heart doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their ſins,<note place="margin">Hom. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oenit.</note> and are unfeinedly ſory for their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, will caſt off all hypo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>criſie, and put on true hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>militie, and lowlineſſe of heart.</p>
               <p>And as they did before give themſelves to unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of life,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> ſo will they hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth with all diligence, give themſelves to innocency, pureneſſe of life, and true godlineſſe.</p>
               <p>The graces of God,<note place="margin">Oecumen.</note> as the flowers of a garden, muſt not only be kept, but alſo dreſſed; that they may have not only a being, but alſo an abounding.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:3292:26"/>
                  <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.</note>Put yee on therefore, as the elect of GOD (holy and belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) bowels of mercies, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, humbleneſſe of minde, meekneſſe, long ſuffering.</p>
               <p>Forbearing one another, and forgiving one another,<note place="margin">4</note> if any have a quarrell againſt any; even as Chriſt forgave you, ſo alſo doe ye.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>And above all things put on Charity, which is the bond of perfectneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Raban.</note>Mercy conſiſteth in giving almes cheerfully, in ſuffering wrong patiently, in refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the rude lovingly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note>It is the ſafety of ſalvation, the ornam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt of faith, and propitiation for ſins.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lyra.</note>Let Chriſts humility alſo bee inwardly in your hearts, and not outwardly, as it is with hypocrites.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:3292:26"/>For unleſſe wee bee beaten downe in humility,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>all.</note> we are no veſſels for Chriſt to dwell in.</p>
               <p>Humilitie is a ſigne of worth; but pride,<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> of empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and vanity.</p>
               <p>If the minde be conſtantly directed to GOD,<note place="margin">Greg moral.</note> whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in this life is bitter unto us, through patience, wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it pleaſant.</p>
               <p>Let a man looke into his heart,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> and ſee if he have Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and then let him ſay, I am borne of GOD.</p>
               <p>Charity is a deſire of the minde to love GOD for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe;<note place="margin">Idem.</note> and to love our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for GOD.</p>
               <p>It is the ſtay of wiſdome,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> the fruit of Faith, the riches of the poore, and the life of them that are dying.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:3292:27"/>
                  <note place="margin">Luther.</note>A Chriſtian life conſiſteth in this; that we deale with faith, and with the heart in things apperteyning to GOD; but uſe our life, and works to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our neighbour.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.</note>For wee are his workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works; which God hath before ordeined, that we ſhould walke in them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hom. de fid. &amp; oper.</note>There is one work, in which be all good works, that is; faith which worketh by charity. If thou have it, thou haſt the ground of all good works.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Luther.</note>GOD will have works done freely, not that wee may me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit any thing therby; but that we may doe them to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of our neighbours, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes our ſincere faith by them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aug.</note>No man doth good works to receive grace by them; but
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3292:27"/>
becauſe he hath firſt received grace, therefore conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he doth good works.</p>
               <p>Behold,<note place="margin">Iohn 5.</note> thou art made whole; ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing happen unto thee.</p>
               <p>Which penance wee ſhall never be able to fulfill,<note place="margin">Hom. de poenit.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſpeciall grace of him, that ſaith,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.5.</note> without me ye can doe nothing.</p>
               <p>It is therfore our parts,<note place="margin">Hom de poenit.</note> if at leaſt wee bee deſirous of the health and ſalvation of our own ſoules, moſt earneſtly to pray to our heavenly father, to aſſiſt us with his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that we may bee able to hearken to the voice of the true Shepheard, and with due obedience to follow the ſame.</p>
               <p>Let us heare the concluſion of the whole matter,<note place="margin">Eccl. 12.</note> feare God, and keepe his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3292:28"/>
for this is the whole duety of man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His aſſurance of Salvation.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 3.</note>HE that beleeveth on the Sonne hath everlaſting life.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.</note>Whom having not ſeene, ye love; in whom, though now yee ſee him not, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving ye rejoyce with joy unſpeakable, and full of glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>Receiving the end of your Faith, even the ſalvation of your ſoules.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Biſh. Fiſher.</note>If wee will enter into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, we muſt not come with a double heart, or wavering faith; but with that which is altogether without doubting, and moſt certain.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hillar.</note>The LORD will have us hope for the Kingdome of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3292:28"/>
Heaven without any doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, for otherwiſe there is no juſtification of faith, if faith be uncertaine.</p>
               <p>The juſt living by faith,<note place="margin">Fulgent.</note> ſaith confidently, I beleeve to ſee the goodneſſe of the LORD in the land of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
               <p>We have hope,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.</note> as an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor of the ſoule, both ſure, and ſtedfaſt, and which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth into that which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Vaile.</p>
               <p>Becauſe ye are ſons,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> GOD hath ſent forth the ſpirit of his ſon into your hearts, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Abba father.</p>
               <p>Wherefore thou art no more a ſervant, but a ſon,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> and if a ſon, then an heire of God through Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Wee leave not a ſinner in<note place="margin">Stapleton.</note> the middeſt of wavering
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3292:29"/>
doubtfulneſſe, but we place him in good, and firme hope; when once his conſcience witneſſeth with him, that he hath truely repented.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aug.</note>There is a kind of glorying in thy conſcience, when thou knoweſt thy faith is ſincere, thy hope certain, thy love without diſſembling.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Altiſiodor.</note>Wee may diſcerne we are in grace, by our good deſire, comfort of minde, and good works.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bernard.</note>The ſpirit by faith revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth to a man the eternall pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God, concerning his future ſalvation; which reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is nothing elſe, but the infuſion of ſpirituall grace, whereby the deeds of the fleſh are mortified, and the man prepared to the kingdome of heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:3292:29"/>Gods truth, and his power,<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dall.</note> is the cauſe of our aſſurance of ſalvation; his truth, becauſe we doe not doubt but he will keepe his promiſe; his power becauſe all things are poſſible to him.</p>
               <p>Herein we looke not upon our own worthines,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> (for then we muſt needs doubt) but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him that promiſed, who will faithfully performe.</p>
               <p>God hath promiſed to thee,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> O man that thou ſhalt live for ever; doſt thou not beleeve it? Beleeve it, beleeve it; for that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he hath already done for thee, is a greater matter than that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he hath promiſed.</p>
               <p>Theſe things have I writ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en unto you that beleeve on the name of the Sonne of God,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.</note> that yee may know that yee have eternall life; and that ye
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3292:30"/>
may beleeve on the name of the Son of GOD.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 15</note>Now the GOD of hope fill you with all joy, and hope in beleeving, that yee may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in hope, through the power of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Gods mercy.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lam. 3.</note>IT is the LORDS mercy that we are not conſumed, becauſe his compaſſions faile not.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 103.</note>Hee hath not dealt with us after our ſinnes, nor rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us according to our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lam. 3.</note>But though hee ſend affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, yet will he have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, according to the multitude of his mercies.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 103.</note>For as the heaven is high
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3292:30"/>
above the earth, ſo great is his mercy towards them that feare him.</p>
               <p>This is the glory of man,<note place="margin">Hieron.</note> that hee may know, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that GOD is the LORD, who giveth mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and juſtice upon the earth.</p>
               <p>The omnipotency of God excelleth two waies;<note place="margin">Hieron.</note> in gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting mercy to the penitent, and puniſhing ſuch as conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in ſin, according to their deſert.</p>
               <p>Hee rejoyceth not of his owne gaine,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> but of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; hee is not grieved for his owne diſpleaſure, but for our deſtruction.</p>
               <p>When hee puniſheth,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> and taketh vengeance; he doth it not with paſſionate anger but with all unſpeakable cle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mency;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3292:31"/>
with the affection of an healer, not of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer.</p>
               <p>How rich art thou, O Lord GOD, in mercy? how great in juſtice? how bountifull in grace?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bernard.</note>Thou beholdeſt the humbie with favour; the Innocent thou judgeſt righteouſly; &amp; ſaveſt ſinners mercifully.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Kempis dial. inter Deum &amp; peccator. de imitat. Chriſti, ſi. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note>Although a ſinner do abide ſtill in the fleſh; yet doe I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him into my favour, ſo that he is not to feare the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confuſion for his ſins co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; but rather to thanke &amp; praiſe God, that old things bee paſſed away, and that all things are become new.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>So gracious and mercifull am I, that alwaies I am more ready to forgive, than thou art to begge forgiveneſſe at
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3292:31"/>
my hands; more ready to give, than thou art to aske.</p>
               <p>To hope well of my goodneſſe,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> is a very token of true humilitie, and of great faith.</p>
               <p>What?<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> looke you to bee all worthy, before you make acceſſe unto mee? And of your ſelfe, when will you bee ſo?</p>
               <p>If onely ſuch as are good,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and worthy, and great, and perfect, ſhould approach unto mee, to whom ſhould ſinners and publicans ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach?</p>
               <p>So then,<note place="margin">Luke 15.</note> what ſaith the Goſpell? Then drew neere unto him all the publicans and ſinners for to heare him.</p>
               <p>Therfore let the unworthy approach,<note place="margin">Kempis.</note> that they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3292:32"/>
worthy; let the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked approach, that they may bee made good; let the weake, and unperfect ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, that they may prove ſtrong, and perfect; yea let all, and every one approach, that they may receive from the abundant ſtreames of the well of life.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 7.</note>Hee which is a thirſt, let him come to me and drinke.<note place="margin">Iſay 55.</note> And he which hath nothing, let him come and buy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſilver, and without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mat 9.</note>Hee that is ſicke, let him come to be healed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 9.</note>Hee that is neither hot, nor cold, let him come to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Kempis.</note>Hee that is fearfull, let him come to bee encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3292:32"/>Hee that is ſorrowfull let him come to bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted.<note place="margin">Idem.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Hee that is wearied with cares,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> let him come to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed with joy.</p>
               <p>Loe, my delight is,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> to bee with the children of men.</p>
               <p>And therefore bee ever mindfull both of your fraile condition,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> and of my glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Majeſtie, and ſo with humble reverence approach boldly into my preſence.</p>
               <p>For I am hee that putteth away thine iniquities,<note place="margin">Iſa. 43.</note> and will not remember thy ſins:</p>
               <p>It is I that juſtifie the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly;<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> and this I doe for my holy Name ſake: yea, and I am ſtill ready to miniſter greater gifts of mercy unto thee.</p>
               <p>Becauſe I doe ever chuſe<note place="margin">Kempis.</note>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:3292:33"/>
to ſhew favour, rather than diſpleaſure, as one who had rather ſpare, than puniſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.</note>Bleſſed bee God, even the Father of our LORD JESUS CHRIST, the Father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and GOD of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Death.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13.14.</note>HEre have wee no conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing City; but wee ſeeke one to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 12.4.</note>Be yee prepared; for the Sonne of man will come at an houre that yee thinke not.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aug.</note>All men know that the day of death will come; yet all, or almoſt all doe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding labour to put it off; yea even thoſe, who beleeve,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3292:33"/>
that after death, they ſhall live more bleſſedly: So great power hath the ſweet fellowſhip of the fleſh, and ſoule.</p>
               <p>Take heed, watch, and pray;<note place="margin">Mar. 13 33.</note> for yee know not when the time is.</p>
               <p>The laſt day of our life is unknowne,<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> that all daies may be obſerved; the remedies are too late provided, when the dangers of death approach.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plato</hi> his opinion is,<note place="margin">Hieron.</note> that the whole life of wiſe men is the meditation of death. Wee ought therefore to premedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate what we ſhall be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and that whether we will, or not, death cannot be lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from us.</p>
               <p>Hee which is aſſured hee ſhall dye,<note place="margin">Gregor.</note> oppoſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe againſt all the deſires of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3292:34"/>
this life. For the perfect life is a meditation of death; which while juſt men doe performe, they eſcape the ſnares of ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aug.</note>That death is not accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted evill, which a good life hath gone before.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.2.</note>Set your affection on things above; not on things of the earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gregor.</note>If wee conſider what, and how great things are promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to us in heaven; all things in earth will be vile, and baſe in our eſtimation: For earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubſtance compared to the heavenly felicity, is but an heavy burthen, not an helpe and ſuccour. This tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall life compared to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, is rather to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a death than a life.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 12.7.</note>Then ſhall the duſt returne
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3292:34"/>
to the earth as it was; and the ſpirit ſhall returne unto God, who gave it.</p>
               <p>They which deſire to bee diſſolved,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> and to bee with Chriſt, doe live patiently, and die cheerfully.</p>
               <p>They are not loſt,<note place="margin">Ambroſ.</note> but ſent before, whom eternity hath received.</p>
               <p>All the daies of my appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time, will I wait,<note place="margin">Iob 14.14.</note> till my change come.</p>
               <p>For to me, to live, is Chriſt;<note place="margin">Phil. 1.21.</note> and to die, is gaine.</p>
               <p>When Chriſt,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.3.</note> who is our life, ſhall appeare; then ſhall ye alſo appeare with him in glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:3292:35"/>
               <head>The laſt Iudgement.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note>IT is appointed unto men once to dye; but after this, the Judgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note>Wee ſhall all ſtand before the Judgement Seat of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.</note>For GOD ſhall bring every worke to judgement, with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſecret thing, whether it be good, or whether it bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron.</note>It is not in us to know the day of Judgement; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alwayes uncertaine of the comming of the Judge, let us ſo live, as if we were, to bee judged the next day.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Idem.</note>If there bee any joy in this preſent life; let it be ſo uſed, that the bitterneſſe of the Judgement to come do not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3292:35"/>
at any time depart out of our memory.</p>
               <p>Nothing doth more ſet forward an honeſt life,<note place="margin">Ambroſ.</note> than to beleeve he ſhall be judged; whom hidden things doe not deceive: evill things doe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend; and good things doe delight.</p>
               <p>That judge is not preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by favour,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> nor led now by mercy, nor corrupted with money, nor appeaſed by ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, or repentance; let the ſoule while it hath time here, labour for it ſelfe by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, ſo long, as here is place for mercy; becauſe there is the place of Juſtice.</p>
               <p>God doth ſo behold our waies, and number our ſteps,<note place="margin">Greg. moral</note> that, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſmaleſt thoughts, and leaſt words remaine not unexamined in his Judgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:3292:36"/>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note>The Lord knoweth the daies of the upright, and their inheritance ſhall be for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>But the wicked ſhall periſh, and the enemies of the Lord ſhall be as the fat of Lambs; they ſhall conſume, into ſmoke ſhall they conſume a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note>In that day wee have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to anſwer for our ſelves, where Heaven, and Earth, the Aire, and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the whole world ſhall witneſſe our ſinnes againſt us. And if all elſe doe hold their peace, our thoughts themſelves, and our works eſpecially ſhall ſtand before our eies, accuſing us before God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bernard.</note>That day will come, in which upright hearts ſhall
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3292:36"/>
more prevaile, than eloquent words; a good Conſcience more, than a full purſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that Judge will not bee deceived by words, nor tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by gifts.</p>
               <p>On the right hand,<note place="margin">Anſelm.</note> will bee our ſinnes accuſing us; on the left hand, innumerable Divels; underneath us, the terrible deepneſſe and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Hell; above, the Judge offended; without, the world burning; within, the conſcience tormenting: there ſhall the juſt ſcarce be ſaved. Alas miſerable ſinner, being thus taken unawares, whither wilt thou fly? for to hide thy ſelfe, is impoſſible, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, is intolerable.</p>
               <p>The rich man alſo died,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.22</note> and was buried;</p>
               <p>And in hell hee lift up his<note place="margin">23.</note>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:3292:37"/>
eyes, being in torments; and ſeeth <hi>Abraham</hi> a farre off, and <hi>Lazarus</hi> in his boſome.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">24.</note>And he cryed, and ſaid; Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abraham,</hi> have mercy on me, and ſend <hi>Lazarus,</hi> that he may dip the tip of his finger in water, &amp; coole my tongue; for I am tormented in this flame.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">25.</note>But <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid; Sonne, remember that thou in thy life time receivedſt thy good things; and likewiſe <hi>Lazarus</hi> evill things, but now hee is comforted, and thou art tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gregor.</note>At the recompence of the laſt Judgement, the wicked doe ſee the upright in peace, that perceiving them in joy, they may not onely bee tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with their owne pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, but alſo with the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3292:37"/>
others proſperity. But the righteous doe alwaies ſee the wicked in torments, that from hence their joy may increaſe; becauſe they ſee the paine, which, by GODS mercie, they have eſcaped; and doe give the greater thanks unto their Maker, when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold that in others, which they might have ſuffered, had they beene forſaken.</p>
               <p>When the Sonne of Man ſhall come in his glory,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> and all the holy Angels with him; then ſhall hee ſit upon the throne of his glory;</p>
               <p>And before him ſhall bee gathered all Nations,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and he ſhall ſeparate them one from another, as a ſhepherd divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his Sheepe from the Goats.</p>
               <p>And he ſhall ſet the ſheepe<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:3292:38"/>
on his right hand; but the Goats on the left.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>Then ſhall the King ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them on his right hand; Come ye bleſſed of my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, inherit the Kingdome prepared for you, from the foundation of the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>Then ſhall he ſay unto them on the left hand, Depart from me, yee curſed, into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting fire, prepared for the Devill, and his Angels.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iude 24.</note>Now, unto him that is able to keep you from falling, &amp; to preſent you faultleſſe, before the preſence of his glorie, with exceeding joy;</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">25.</note>To the onely wiſe GOD, our Saviour, bee Glory, and Majeſty, Dominion, and power, now, and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:3292:38"/>
               <head>FOURE HELPS to the amendment of Life.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> Prayer.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Reading the holy Scriptures.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> Hearing Gods Word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4.</hi> Worthy receiving the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Body and Bloud of our Lord.</item>
               </list>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1 <hi>Prayer.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> LORD, I know,<note place="margin">Ier. 10.23.</note> that the way of man is not in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: it is not in man that walketh to direct his ſteps.</p>
                  <p>It is written in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets;<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.45.</note>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:3292:39"/>
And they ſhall be all taught of GOD; Every man therefore that hath heard, and hath learned of the father, commeth unto me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 15.5.</note>I am the vine, yee are the branches; he that abideth in me, and I in him, the ſame bringeth forth much fruit: For without me, yee can doe nothing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.8.</note>I will therefore, that men pray every where, lifting up holy hands, without wrath, or doubting.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iude 20.</note>Building up your ſelves on your moſt holy faith, praying in the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Mat 6.7.</note>But when ye pray, uſe not vaine repetitions, as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then doe, for they thinke, that they ſhall be heard, for their much ſpeaking.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">8.</note>Be not ye therefore like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3292:39"/>
them; for your heavenly father knoweth, what things yee have need of, before yee aske him.</p>
                  <p>What things ſoever ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, when ye pray,<note place="margin">Mar. 11.24.</note> beleeve that ye receive them, and ye ſhall have them.</p>
                  <p>Let us lift up our heart,<note place="margin">Lam 3.41.</note> with our hands, unto God in the heavens.</p>
                  <p>It is not in man to direct his owne waies;<note place="margin">
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dall.</note> and therfore we muſt pray to God continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, to guide us for his glory, and our ſoules comfort.</p>
                  <p>Praier is a thing moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for all men, at all times,<note place="margin">Hom. de orat.</note> and in all places.</p>
                  <p>It is the firſt thing wherwith a righteous life beginneth,<note place="margin">Hooker.</note> &amp; the laſt with w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> it doth end.</p>
                  <p>It is the turning of a godly &amp; humble minde to God,<note place="margin">Hugo.</note> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3292:40"/>
by Faith, Hope, and Charity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iſidor.</note>Neither is it a worke of the lips, but of the heart. GOD intendeth not the words, but beholdeth the heart of him that prayeth. It is better to pray with the heart, in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, without the ſound of the voyce, than in words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, without the affection of the minde.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iuſt. Mart.</note>We ſacrifice unto GOD, without ceaſing, the ſacrifice of praiſe, ſincere prayer, and the ſweet ſavour of good works.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Perkins.</note>Our prayers are our ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and Chriſt alone is the Altar, whereon wee muſt offer them to GOD the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Aug.</note>Faith is the fountaine of prayer, neither can the ſtream
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3292:40"/>
run, if the head of the Spring bee dryed up.</p>
                  <p>When prayer is faithfull,<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> humble, and fervent, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it entreth into Heaven; from whence it cannot returne empty.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Reading the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EZra</hi> the Prieſt read in the Booke of the Law,<note place="margin">Nehemiah 8.3.</note> from the morning, untill the mid day, before the men, and the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; thoſe that could underſtand; and the eares of all the people were attentive unto the Book of the Law.</p>
                  <p>The children of Iſrael read in the Booke of the Law,<note place="margin">9.3.</note> of the LORD their GOD, one fourth part of the day;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3292:41"/>
and another fourth part they confeſſed, and worſhipped the Lord their God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 13.15.</note>After the reading of the Law, and the Prophets, the Rulers of the Synagogue ſent to <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> ſaying; Ye men, and brethren, if yee have any word of exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the people; ſay on.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note>The reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is a great defence againſt ſinne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Hom. de legen. Scrip.</note>Whoſoever is diligent to read this word, &amp; in his heart to print that he readeth, ſhall finde his affection diminiſhed towards this world; and his deſire of heavenly things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>There is nothing that ſo much ſtrengtheneth our faith; that ſo much keepeth up
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3292:41"/>
the innocency, &amp; pureneſſe of heart, and of outward godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and converſation, as continuall reading, and recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Gods word.</p>
                  <p>Many times,<note place="margin">Kempis</note> through our owne curioſity, we profit lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in reading, while we ſtand to diſcuſſe things, which ought ſimply to be beleeved.</p>
                  <p>If thou deſireſt to reap commodity,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> reade with all humility, ſimplicity, &amp; zeale; and never covet to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted learned.</p>
                  <p>Read it therefore with an humble, and lowly heart,<note place="margin">Hom. de legen. Scrip</note> to the end you may glorifie GOD, and not your ſelfe, with the knowledge of it. Pray daily to GOD, that hee would direct your reading to good ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:3292:42"/>
                     <note place="margin">Hom. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort. to reade and know Script.</note>Unto a Chriſtian man no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more neceſſary, or profitable, than the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of holy Scripture: In which is conteyned GODS true Word, ſetting forth his glory and mans duty.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Socrat.</note>It was the cuſtome of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> the Emperour, that to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his houſhold, he ſpent much time in reading the Scriptures, and ſinging of Pſalmes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Hom. de leg. Scriptur.</note>Wherefore as you have any zeale to the pure honouring of GOD, and regard to your owne ſoules, and the life that is to come; apply your ſelves, chiefly above all things, to read, and heare GODS Word; Marke di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently therein, what his will is you ſhall doe, and withall endevour, apply
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3292:42"/>
your ſelves to follow the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſed is he that readeth,<note place="margin">Revel. 1.3.</note> and they that heare the words of this Prophecie, and keepe thoſe things which are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten therein.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>3.</hi> Hearing the Word preached.</head>
                  <p>EArly in the morning Jeſus came into the Temple,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.2.</note> and all the people came unto him, and he ſate downe, and taught them.</p>
                  <p>In the day time Jeſus was teaching in the Temple,<note place="margin">Luk. 21.37</note> and at night he went out, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boad in the Mount, that is called the Mount of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lives.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:3292:43"/>
                     <note place="margin">38.</note>And all the people came early in the morning to him in the Temple, to heare him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 13.44</note>The next Sabbath day came almoſt the whole City of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochia</hi> together, to heare the word of God preached by <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rnabas.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 8.5.</note>Then came <hi>Philip</hi> into the City of Samaria, &amp; preached Chriſt unto them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">6.</note>And the people gave heed unto thoſe things, which <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> ſpake, with one accord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 17.11.</note>The Jewes of Berea were more noble than thoſe in Theſſalonica, in that they received the Word with all readineſſe of minde; and ſearched the Scriptures daily, whether thoſe things were ſo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Wickliff.</note>That the hearing of the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3292:43"/>
Word, and Law of GOD, is commmanded to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it is evident, both by the old, and new Law.</p>
                  <p>Take opportunity to heare preaching; and to prove,<note place="margin">Graſhop.</note> by the Scriptures, that which is taught.</p>
                  <p>The firſt,<note place="margin">Bayne.</note> and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall meanes to uphold a Chriſtian life in godli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, is, the Word of GOD, read, preached, and heard, as the Lord preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</p>
                  <p>Where there is a good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of teaching,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, skill, love, and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, we muſt be attentive, and reverent in hearing.</p>
                  <p>As drinke is pleaſant to them that be dry,<note place="margin">Hom. de leg. Scriptur.</note> and meat to them that be hungry; ſo is the reading, hearing ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3292:44"/>
and ſtudying of the holy Scriptures, to them that bee deſirous to know God, or themſelves, and to doe his will.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Bayne.</note>The ordinarie preaching of the Word, is a ſingular meanes provided for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of GODS elect, and for their growing in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian life.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>4. <hi>Sacraments.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. Ang.</note>CHriſt hath ordained in his Church two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments onely, as generally ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation; that is to ſay, Baptiſme, and the Supper of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Coſler.</note>A Sacrament is an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and viſible ſigne, of a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3292:44"/>
divine, inviſible grace, inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by Chriſt, by vertue whereof, the receiver ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth grace and ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>In Sacraments,<note place="margin">Bellar.</note> both the matter, and words muſt bee inſtituted by GOD; and are not alterable by man, either by addition, or diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>They are therefore called Sacraments,<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> becauſe one thing is ſeene in them, and another thing underſtood. That which is ſeene, hath a bodily kinde, forme, and ſhew; but that which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, hath ſpirituall fruit.</p>
                  <p>Wee muſt not conſider,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> what they be, but what they ſignifie.</p>
                  <p>It is a dangerous matter,<note place="margin">Idem.</note>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:3292:45"/>
to take the ſigne in ſtead of the thing that is ſignified.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The holy Euchariſt, or Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Body and Bloud of our Lord.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note>AS they were eating, Jeſus tooke bread, and bleſſed it, and brake it, and gave it to his diſciples, and ſaid; Take, eat, this is my body.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>And he tooke the cup, and gave thankes, and gave it to them, ſaying; Drinke yee all of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>For this is my Blood of the new Teſtament, which is ſhed for many, for the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſins.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:3292:45"/>In ſtead of the Fleſh,<note place="margin">Beda.</note> and Blood of the Lambe, Chriſt hath ordained the Sacrament of his Body and Bloud, in the figure of bread and wine.</p>
               <p>Neither doe wee receive them, as common bread,<note place="margin">Iuſt. Mart.</note> nor as common drinke.</p>
               <p>The bread which is of the earth,<note place="margin">Iren.</note> receiving the invocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God, is not now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bread, but the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, conſiſting of two things; earthly, and heavenly.</p>
               <p>Chriſt taking bread,<note place="margin">Tertul.</note> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributing it to his diſciples, made it his body, ſaying, this is my Body, that is to ſay, this is a figure of my body.</p>
               <p>It is evident,<note place="margin">Bertram.</note> that the bread and wine, are figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively the body and bloud of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>By the commandement and<note place="margin">Iſidor.</note>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:3292:46"/>
authority of Chriſt, we call it the Body and Bloud of Chriſt; becauſe that, though it bee made of the fruits of the earth, it is yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſanctified, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Sacrament, GODS Spirit working inviſibly therein.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bertram.</note>That body wherein Chriſt ſuffered, was his proper, and true body; having no my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall, or figurative matter in it. But this latter, is a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall body; ſhewing one thing outwardly in figure, and inwardly repreſenting another thing, through the underſtanding, and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eccle. Angl.</note>The body of Chriſt is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, taken, and eaten in the Supper onely, after an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly manner. And the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3292:46"/>
meane, whereby the body of Chriſt is received in the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is Faith.</p>
               <p>To beleeve in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> is the eating of the Bread of Life; prepare not your mouths; prepare your hearts.</p>
               <p>This is to eat that living bread, to beleeve in Chriſt;<note place="margin">Clem. Alex.</note> that is to ſay, with love to cleave faſt unto him.</p>
               <p>This is to drinke the bloud of Jeſus;<note place="margin">Idem.</note> to be made partaker of his immortality.</p>
               <p>This is therefore,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> to eat that meat, and drinke that drinke; To dwell in Chriſt, and to have Chriſt dwelling in us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:3292:47"/>
               <head>A remembrance of the death, and paſſion of our Saviour Christ.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.</note>THe LORD JESUS, the ſame night, in which he was betrayed, tooke bread;</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>And when hee had given thanks, he brake it, and ſaid; Take, eat, this is my body, which is broken for you; this doe in remembrance of me.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>After the ſame manner alſo hee tooke the cup, when hee had ſupped, ſaying; This cup is the new Teſtament in my bloud; this doe, as oft as yee drinke it, in remembrance of me.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.</note>For as often as yee eat this bread, and drink this cup, yee
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3292:47"/>
doe ſhew the Lords death till he come.</p>
               <p>The Sacrament of the Lords Supper was ordained for the continuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the ſacrifice of the death of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. Ang.</note> and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits which we receive there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.</p>
               <p>This bread, and this cup,<note place="margin">Bertram.</note> which is called the body, and blood of CHRIST, doe lively repreſent, or ſet out the remembrance of the Lords paſſion, or d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath; even as himſelfe hath ſaid in the Goſpell;<note place="margin">Luke 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Do this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me:</hi> which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> expoundeth, ſaying,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>As often as ye eat this bread, and drink this cup ye ſhew the Lords death till hee come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Lord gave unto his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,<note place="margin">Walfrid. Strab.</note> the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his body
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3292:48"/>
and Bloud, in the ſubſtance of bread, and wine; and therin taught them, to celebrate the memory of his moſt bleſſed Paſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ammon.</note>Having taken the bread, then afterwards the cup of wine, and teſtified it, to bee his Body and Bloud; he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, to eat, and drinke thereof; foraſmuch as it was the memoriall of his future paſſion and death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Worthy Receivers.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.</note>BUt let a man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eat of that Bread, and drinke of that Cup.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>For he that eateth, and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth unworthily, eateth, and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3292:48"/>
drinketh damnation to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; not diſcerning the LORDS body.</p>
               <p>They which are of a cleane conſcience, upright in heart,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. moral.</note> and of an unreprovable life, may alwaies come to this Table; but they, which are not ſo, may not once ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto it.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> thus ſpeaketh;<note place="margin">Alcinnus.</note> I like well of your humility, that you preſume not to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the Body, and Bloud of Chriſt; But it were better you would depart from your iniquities; and being made cleane by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, would take the Body, and Bloud of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Hee is a worthy receiver,<note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> that, remembring the benefit of Chriſt his paſſion, lifteth up his heart unto the living God with
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3292:49"/>
his heart unto the living God with comfort, abhorreth all bitter drinks of ſinne, and all ſavour of carnall pleaſures is to him, as ſharp, and ſoure vineger. And the ſinner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing converted, receiving the holy myſteries of the Lords Supper, giveth thankes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to GOD, and boweth down his head, knowing that his ſinnes be forgiven, and that he is made cleane, and perfect; and his ſoule (which GOD hath ſanctified) he rendreth to God againe, as a faithfull pledge; and glorieth with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaying; Now is it not I, that live; but it is Chriſt, that liveth in me.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cyprian.</note>The worthy eating, is our dwelling in him, and our drinking is, as it were, our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporating in him; being
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3292:49"/>
ſubject to him, in obedience; joyned to him, in our wils; and united, in our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Foure things moſt requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite,<note place="margin">Eccle. Angl.</note> to make us meet parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the holy myſteries.</p>
               <p>To repent us truly for our <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſinnes paſt.</p>
               <p>To have a lively, and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> faith in Chriſt, our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
               <p>To amend our lives, and be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in charity with all men.</p>
               <p>To give moſt humble, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> hearty thankes to GOD, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, for the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world, by the death, and paſſion of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:3292:50"/>
               <head>Vnworthy Receivers.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. Ang.</note>THe wicked, and ſuch as be void of a lively faith, although they doe carnally, and viſibly preſſe with their teeth (as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith) the Sacrament of the body, and bloud of Chriſt; yet, in no wiſe, are they partakers of Chriſt, but rather, to their condemnation, doe eat, and drink the ſigne, or Sacrament of ſo great a thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aug.</note>Outwardly, they have the Sacrament of Chriſts body; but the thing it ſelfe, inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their hearts, they have not; And therefore they eat, and drink their owne judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Idem.</note>Neither Heretike, nor ſuch as profeſſe a true faith in their
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3292:50"/>
mouths, and in their living ſhew the contrary, are to bee accompted among the mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt. Therefore it may not be ſaid, that any of them, doe eat the body of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>As corporall meat,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> finding the belly poſſeſſed with evill humours, doth more offend, and hurt, and helpe nothing at all: So alſo this ſpirituall food, finding a man polluted with ſinne, will rather de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroy him; not by its owne nature; but by the Receivers corruption.</p>
               <p>For he that hath yet a will to ſinne,<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> I account him rather more burthened, by receiving the Euchariſt, than cleanſed: Therefore, albeit a man doe moderate ſinne, purpoſing not to ſinne hereafter, yet let
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3292:51"/>
him make ſatisfaction by teares, and prayers, when hee intendeth to communicate, truſting in the mercy of God; who upon godly confeſſion of his iniquity, uſeth to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: Then let him approach unto the Euchariſt ſafely and without feare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Tranſubſtantiation.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. Ang.</note>TRanſubſtantiation, or the change of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of bread, and wine, in the Supper of the Lord, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be proved by holy writ: but it is repugnant to the plaine words of Scripture, overthroweth the nature of a Sacrament, and hath given occaſion to many ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:3292:51"/>The myſticall ſignes,<note place="margin">Theodoret.</note> after conſecration, depart not from their owne nature; for they abide ſtill in their former ſubſtance, figure, and forme; and may bee ſeene, and tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, as before.</p>
               <p>Touching the ſubſtance of the creatures,<note place="margin">Bertram.</note> they abide the ſame, after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, as they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>Before the bread be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, wee call it bread;<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> but when GODS grace hath ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified it, by meanes of the Prieſt, it is delivered from the name of bread, and is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted worthy the name of the LORDS body, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the nature of bread remaine ſtill.</p>
               <p>Hee honoured the viſible<note place="margin">Theodoret.</note> ſignes with the name of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:3292:52"/>
his body and bloud; not changing the nature; but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding grace, to nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Idem.</note>For he would have the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the divine myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, not to reſpect the nature of thoſe things, which are ſeene; but to beleeve the change which is done by grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Scot.</note>We cannot be brought to determine tranſubſtantiation, either by any plaine place of Scripture, or ſentence of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient father.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cyril.</note>For like as when hee was converſant here in earth, as man; yet then he filled hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and did not leave the company of Angels: Even ſo being now in heaven with his fleſh; yet he filleth the earth, and is in them that love him, by the power of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:3292:52"/>Although Chriſt be corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in heaven;<note place="margin">Gre. Valen. Ieſ.</note> yet he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the faithfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants, in this Sacrament, truly; both ſpiritually, by the mouth of the mind; through a moſt neere conjunction of Chriſt, with the ſoule of the Receiver, by faith: And alſo ſacramentally, with the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily mouth; receiving not Chriſt (according to his locall preſence) but bread, and wine, as ſeales, and ſignes of the promiſe of redemption in his body and blood.</p>
               <p>According to his body,<note place="margin">Greg. Naz.</note> hee is within the limitation of place; according to his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and Godhead, he is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the limitation of any place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:3292:53"/>
               <head>To be received in both kinds.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. Ang.</note>THe cup of the Lord is not to be denied to the lay people; for both the parts of the Lords Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by Chriſts ordinance, and commandement, ought to be adminiſtred to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian men alike.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vaſques Ieſ.</note>Each kind in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (as it is a part of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament) hath a divers ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by it ſelfe: And each kind in this Sacrament, doth worke its owne effect, by it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Durand.</note>The bread ſignifieth the body, and not the bloud; and the wine ſignifieth the bloud, and not the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Alex. Hales.</note>Whole Chriſt is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3292:53"/>
under each kind, by way of Sacrament; but the fleſh onely, under the forme of bread; and the bloud, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the forme of wine.</p>
               <p>In the Primitive Church,<note place="margin">Durand.</note> all preſent at the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, did participate of the cup; becauſe all the Apoſtles did ſo, our Lord ſaying unto them; Drink ye all of this.</p>
               <p>Wee have underſtood,<note place="margin">Gelaſ. Pap.</note> that ſome, having onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a portion of Chriſts body, doe abſtaine from the cup of his ſacred bloud; But ſith they are moved, by a fond ſuperſtition (which I know not) thus to abſtaine; either let them receive the whole Sacrament, or bee put from all together; for there can bee no diviſion of this Sacrament, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:3292:54"/>
high myſtery, without great ſacriledge.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ignat.</note>I exhort you to imbrace one faith, one manner of preaching, and uſe of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, of the LORDS Supper; for the fleſh of the LORD JESUS, is one, and his bloud, one, that was ſhed for us: There is one bread alſo, broken for all; and one cup, diſtributed unto all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:3292:54"/>
               <head>The Prayer before receiving the Communion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmighty GOD,<note place="margin">Eccle. Angl.</note> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, Maker of of all things, Judge of all men, we acknowledge, and bewaile our manifold ſinnes and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, which wee, from time to time, moſt grievouſly have committed, by thought, word, and deed, againſt thy divine Majeſty; provoking, moſt juſtly, thy wrath, and indignation againſt us; We doe earneſtly repent, and be hartily ſory, for theſe our miſdoings; the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:3292:55"/>
of them, is grievous unto us, the burthen of them is intolerable; Have mercy upon us, have mercy upon us, moſt mercifull Father, for thy Sonne, our Lord Jeſus Chriſts ſake, forgive us all that is paſt: And grant, that we may ever hereafter ſerve, and pleaſe thee, in newneſſe of life, to the honour and glory of thy holy name, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord; <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:3292:55"/>
               <head>The Prayer after receiving the Communion.</head>
               <p>O Lord,<note place="margin">Eccl. Angl.</note> our heavenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wee, thy humble ſervants, intirely deſire thy fatherly goodneſſe, merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to accept this our ſacrifice, of praiſe, and thankſgiving, moſt humbly beſeeching thee, to grant, that by the merits, and death of thy Son Jeſus Chriſt, and through faith in his bloud, wee, and all thy whole Church, may obtaine remiſſion of our ſinnes, and all other bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of his paſſion. And here we offer, and preſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, O Lord, our ſelves,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:3292:56"/>
our ſoules, and bodies, to be a reaſonable, holy, and lively ſacrifice, unto thee; Humbly beſeeching thee, that all we, which bee partakers of this holy Communion, may bee fulfilled with thy grace, and heavenly benediction. And although wee bee unworthy through our manifold ſins, to offer unto thee, any ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; yet we beſeech thee, to accept this, our bounden du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſervice; not weighing our merits, but pardoning our offences, through Jeſus Chriſt, our Lord; by whom, and with whom, in the unity of the holy Ghoſt, all honor, and glory be unto thee, O fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Almighty, world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:3292:56"/>
               <head>A Prayer before reading the holy Scriptures.</head>
               <p>O Gracious GOD,<note place="margin">Graſhop.</note> and moſt mercifull father, which haſt vouchſafed us, the rich and pretious jewell, of thy holy word: Aſſiſt us, with thy ſpirit, that it may be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in our hearts, to our ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting comfort; to reforme us, to renew us, according to thine owne image, to build us up, and edifie us, into the perfect building, of thy ſonne Chriſt Jeſus; ſanctifying, and increaſing in us, all heavenly vertues. Grant this, O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:3292:57"/>
               <head>A Prayer for faith.</head>
               <p>MOſt mercifull, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Father, I beſeech thee, for Chriſt Jeſus ſake, to ſtrengthen, and increaſe my faith, that I may goe forward in all godlineſſe. And grant, O Lord, that my faith may bee builded upon the rock, Chriſt Jeſus; that I be not carried away with every blaſt of vain doctrine, but, through faith in thee, I may be, as an invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible fortreſſe, to my enemy, the Devill, ſo that he may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver prevaile againſt me. Alſo Lord, I pray thee, let not my faith bee an idle faith, but a working faith; that daily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth, from one good work, to another, and in the end, to life everlaſting, there to reigne with thee, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:3292:57"/>
               <head>For Repentance.</head>
               <p>MAke cleane my heart, O moſt gracious God, with the water of thy heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grace, from all the ſtaines, and corruptions of ſin; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appeareth moſt vile and loathſome in thy ſight. Sprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle it with the hyſop of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained repentance, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction; that being waſhed in the moſt cleare fountaine of thy grace, I may become whiter than ſnow; and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more ſerve thee, in holineſſe, and pureneſſe of life, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:3292:58"/>
               <head>A ſhort and effectuall Prayer.</head>
               <p>I Moſt humbly beſeech thee, O moſt gracious God, and loving Father; to take from me, the ſway of mine owne affections: Incline mine heart wholly, to the obedience of thy heavenly will: Suppreſſe, and quench in me, all deſires whatſoever, that may alienate, and withdraw me to wander, from the way of thy teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: Grant unto mee ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, the aſſiſtance of thy holy Spirit, to conduct, and bring me, to the inheritance of thy everlaſting kingdome; for the love of thy onely Son, our Saviour Jeſus CHRIST, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:3292:58"/>
               <head>The generall Confeſsion.</head>
               <p>ALmighty,<note place="margin">Eccl. Angl. in liturg.</note> and moſt mercifull Father, I have erred, and ſtrayed from thy waies, like a loſt ſheep; I have followed too much, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, and deſires of my owne heart; I have offended againſt thy holy Lawes; I have left undone, thoſe things, which I ought to have done; and have done, thoſe things, which I ought not to have done: And there is no health in me; but thou, O LORD, have mercie upon me, miſerable offender; Spare thou mee, O GOD, which confeſſe my faults;
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:3292:59"/>
reſtore thou mee, that am penitent, according to thy promiſes, declared unto man-kind, in Chriſt Jeſu our Lord; And grant, O moſt mercifull father, for his ſake, that I may hereafter live a godly, righteous, and a ſober life, to the glory of thy holy name. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:3292:59"/>
               <head>A Prayer for the Morning.</head>
               <p>O Lord,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. Ang. in Liturg.</note> our heavenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Almighty, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting GOD; I moſt humbly thanke thee, for thy great mercy, and goodneſſe, in keeping, and preſerving me from all perils, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers this night paſt, and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging me ſafely to the begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning of this day: Defend me, O Lord, in the ſame, with thy mighty power; And grant, that this day I fall into no ſinne, neither run in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any kind of danger, but
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:3292:60"/>
that all my doings, may bee ordered by thy governance; to doe alwaies that, which is righteous in thy ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt, our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our father which art in heaven, hallowed, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:3292:60"/>
               <head>A Prayer for all times.</head>
               <p>O Almightie Lord,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. Ang. Ibid.</note> and everliving God, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe, I beſeech thee, to direct, ſanctifie, and governe, both my heart, and body, in the waies of thy Laws, and in the works of thy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; That through thy moſt mighty protection, both here and ever, I may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, in body, and ſoule, through our LORD, and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:3292:61"/>
               <head>A Prayer before going to bed.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eternall, and ever-living GOD, I render unto thy divine Majeſtie, moſt humble, and hearty thankes, for thy mercifull preſervation of mee this day, from the hands of mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; Beſeeching thee, of thy fatherly goodneſſe, and mercy, to remit and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all mine offences, which in thought, word, and deed, I have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:3292:61"/>
againſt thy holy Laws and Commandements: Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, that, by thy moſt gracious protection, I may bee defended, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved this night, from all perils, and dangers, both of body, and ſoule; that mine eyes may ſleep quietly, my body reſt ſecurely, and my ſoule ever watch unto thee conſtantly; ſo that I never conſent to the temptations, and allurements of Satan; but by the continuall directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and aſſiſtance of thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly grace, I may come to thine eternall glory, through Jeſus Chriſt, our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Father which art in heaven, hallowed, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="Psalm">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:3292:62"/>
               <head>A Pſalme of contrition, and confeſsion.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 38.</note>O Lord, rebuke me not in thy wrath: neither cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten me in thy hot diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>I am troubled, I am bowed downe greatly; I goe mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all the day long.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">22.</note>I am powred out like water, and all my bones are out of joint, my heart is like wax, it is melted in the middeſt of my bowels.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">31.</note>I am forgotten, as a dead man out of minde; I am like a broken veſſell.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">41.</note>Lord be mercifull unto me; heale my ſoule, for I have ſinned againſt thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">38.</note>All my deſire is before thee; and my groaning is not hid from thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:3292:62"/>For I will declare mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity;<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> I will be ſorry for my ſinne.</p>
               <p>The ſacrifices of God are a broken ſpirit; a broken,<note place="margin">51.</note> and a contrite heart, O Lord, thou wilt not deſpiſe.</p>
               <p>O GOD,<note place="margin">69.</note> thou knoweſt my fooliſhneſſe; and my ſinnes are not hid from thee.</p>
               <p>I have gone aſtray,<note place="margin">119.</note> like a loſt ſheep; ſeeke thy ſervant, for I doe not forget thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</p>
               <p>I acknowledge my tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions;<note place="margin">51.</note> and my ſin is ever before me.</p>
               <p>Againſt thee,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> thee onely have I ſinned; and done this evill in thy ſight.</p>
               <p>There is no ſoundneſſe in my fleſh,<note place="margin">38.</note> becauſe of thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, neither is there any reſt in my bones, becauſe of my ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:3292:63"/>
                  <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>For mine iniquities are gone over my head; as an heavy burthen, they are too heavy for me.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>My wounds ſtinke, and are corrupt, becauſe of my foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">40.</note>Innumerable evils have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed me about, mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities have taken hold upon me, ſo that I am not able to looke up; they are moe than the haires of mine head, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may heart faileth me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="Psalm">
               <head>A Pſalme for remiſsion.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note>HAve mercy upon me, O God, according to thy loving kindneſſe; according to the multitude of thy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercies, blot out my tranſgreſſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:3292:63"/>Waſh mee thorowly from mine iniquity;<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and cleanſe me from my ſinne.</p>
               <p>Purge me with hyſop,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and I ſhall be cleane; waſh me, &amp; I ſhall be whiter than ſnow.</p>
               <p>For thy name ſake, O Lord,<note place="margin">25.</note> pardon mine iniquity; for it is great.</p>
               <p>Remember not the ſins of my youth,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> nor my tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; according to thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy remember thou mee, for thy goodneſſe ſake, O Lord.</p>
               <p>Turne thee unto me,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and have mercy upon me; for I am deſolate, and afflicted.</p>
               <p>Looke upon mine afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and my paine;<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give all my ſins.</p>
               <p>O keepe my ſoule,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me; let me not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, for I put my truſt in thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:3292:64"/>
                  <note place="margin">39.</note>Deliver mee from all my tranſgreſſions; make me not the reproach of the fooliſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">31.</note>Make thy face to ſhine up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy ſervant; ſave me, for thy mercy ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">51.</note>Hide thy face from my ſins; &amp; blot out all mine iniquities.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>Create in me a cleane heart, and renew a right ſpirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>Caſt mee not away from thy preſence; and take not thy holy ſpirit from me.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">141.</note>Mine eyes are unto thee, O Lord God, in thee is my truſt; leave not my ſoule deſtitute.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="Psalm">
               <head>A Pſalme for mercy, and direction.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 69.</note>HEare mee, O Lord, for thy loving kindneſſe is good; turne unto me, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:3292:64"/>
to the multitude of thy tender mercies.</p>
               <p>Remember, O Lord,<note place="margin">25.</note> thy tender mercies, and thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindneſſe; for they have beene ever of old.</p>
               <p>Be mercifull unto mee,<note place="margin">86.</note> O Lord; for I cry unto thee daily.</p>
               <p>Shew mee thy waies,<note place="margin">25.</note> O Lord; teach me thy paths.</p>
               <p>Lead me in thy truth,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and teach me, for thou art the God of my ſalvation; on thee doe I wait all the day.</p>
               <p>O ſend out thy light,<note place="margin">43.</note> &amp; thy truth, let them leade me; let them bring me to thy holy hill, and to thy tabernacles.</p>
               <p>Cauſe me to heare thy loving kindneſſe in the morning;<note place="margin">143.</note> for in thee doe I truſt; cauſe me to know the way wherin I ſhould walke; for I lift up my ſoule unto thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:3292:65"/>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>Teach me to doe thy will, for thou art my God, thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is good; lead me into the land of uprightneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">40.</note>With-hold not thou thy tender mercies from me, O Lord; let thy loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and thy truth, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally preſerve me.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">119.</note>Order my ſteps in thy word, and let not any iniquity have dominion over me.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">86.</note>Teach me thy way, O Lord, I will walk in thy truth; unite my heart to feare thy name.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">39.</note>Lord, make mee to know mine end, and the meaſure of my daies, what it is; that I may know how fraile I am.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="Psalm">
               <head>A Pſalme of confidence in Gods mercie.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 23.</note>THe Lord is my ſhepherd; I ſhall not want.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:3292:65"/>He maketh me to lie down in greene paſtures;<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> he leadeth me beſide the ſtill waters.</p>
               <p>He reſtoreth my ſoule;<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> he leadeth mee in the paths of righteouſneſſe, for his Names ſake.</p>
               <p>Yea though I walk through the valley of the ſhadow of death, I will feare none evill;<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> for thou art with me, thy rod, &amp; thy ſtaffe, they comfort me.</p>
               <p>I will abide in thy Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle for ever,<note place="margin">61.</note> I will truſt in the covert of thy wings.</p>
               <p>Becauſe thou haſt been my helpe;<note place="margin">63.</note> therefore in the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of thy wings will I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce.</p>
               <p>For thou haſt beene a ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for me;<note place="margin">61.</note> and a ſtrong tower from mine enemies.</p>
               <p>I will come into thy houſe,<note place="margin">5.</note> in the multitude of thy mercy:
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:3292:66"/>
&amp; in thy feare, will I worſhip towards thine holy Temple.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">62.</note>My ſoule, wait thou onely upon God; for my expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is from him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>He only is my rock, and my ſalvation; he is my defence, I ſhall not be moved.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">40.</note>Bleſſed is that man, that maketh the Lord his truſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="104" type="Psalm">
               <head>A Pſalme of praiſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 104.</note>I Will ſing unto the Lord, as long as I live; I will ſing praiſe unto my God, whiles I have my being.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">7.</note>I will praiſe the Lord, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his righteouſneſſe, I will ſing praiſe unto the name of the Lord, moſt high.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">8.</note>O Lord, our God, how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent is thy name in all the earth; who haſt ſet thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:3292:66"/>
above the Heavens.</p>
               <p>I will give thee thankes in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation:<note place="margin">35.</note> I will praiſ thee, among much people.</p>
               <p>I will worſhip towards thy holy Temple,<note place="margin">138.</note> and praiſe thy name, for thy loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and for thy truth: for thou haſt magnified thy word above all thy name.</p>
               <p>I will extoll thee, my God,<note place="margin">145.</note> O King, and I will bleſſe thy name, for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>Every day will I bleſſe thee;<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and I will praiſe thy name, for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>My mouth ſhall ſpeake the praiſe of the Lord;<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and let all fleſh bleſſe his holy name, for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>The Lord liveth,<note place="margin">18.</note> and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be my rock; and let the God of my ſalvation be exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:3292:67"/>
                  <note place="margin">28.</note>Bleſſed be the Lord, becauſe hee hath heard the voyce of my ſupplications.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">41.</note>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael, from everlaſting to everlaſting: <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="epigraph">
               <head>ECCLES. 12.12.</head>
               <q>
                  <p>OF making many books there is no end, and much ſtudy is a wearineſſe of the fleſh.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">13.</note>Let us heare the concluſion of the whole matter: feare GOD, and keepe his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, for this is the whole duty of man.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Collectanea</hi> T. P.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>SA. BAKER.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iunii</hi> 30. 1637.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3292:67"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
